Register of the Fred M. Hechinger Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- New York Times and New York Times Foundation File, 1958-1989.; See also Oversize File.
  - Travel orders (Folder 69: 8)
  - Miscellany (Folder 69: 9)
- Career File, 1977-1990; See also New York Times and New York Times Foundation File
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, printed matter, and miscellany relating to Fred Hechinger's involvement with a variety of organizations, arranged alphabetically by name of organization and therein by physical form.
  - Academy for Educational Development
    - General (Folder 69: 10)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1989 (Folder 69: 11)
    - Memoranda and minutes of meetings, 1981-1983 (Folder 69: 12)
  - American Council on Education (Box 70)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1987 (Folder 70: 1)
    - Printed matter (Folder 70: 2)
    - Reports (Folder 70: 3)
  - Business Committee for the Arts, Inc. Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials (Folder 70: 4)
  - Carnegie Corporation of New York
    - General (Folder 70: 5)
    - Correspondence
      - 1978-1987 (Folder 70: 6)
      - 1988 - 1989 June (Folder 70: 7)
      - 1989 July – 1990 October (Box-folder 71: 1)
    - Memoranda
      - 1983 - 1988 August (Folder 71: 2)
      - 1988 September – 1990 August (Folder 71: 3)
    - Minutes of meetings of Board of Trustees
      - General (Folder 71: 4)
      - 1984 (Folder 71: 5)
      - 1985 (Folder 71: 6)
  - Carnegie Forum on Education and the Economy
    - General (Folder 71: 7)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Folder 71: 8)
    - Memoranda, 1985-1987 (Folder 71: 9)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. Correspondence, 1977-1990 (Folder 71: 10)
  - Corporate Council on the Liberal Arts (Box 72)
    - General (Folder 72: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Folder 72: 2)
  - Education Writers Association (EWA). Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Folder 72: 3)
  - Foreign Policy Association
    - Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Folder 72: 4)
    - Memoranda, 1987-1990 (Folder 72: 5)
    - Minutes of meetings
      - 1987-1988 (Folder 72: 6)
      - 1989-1990 (Folder 72: 7)
    - Miscellany (Folder 72: 8)
  - New York Academy of Sciences. Correspondence, 1985 (Folder 72: 9)
- Grace Hechinger File, 1957-1985.
  Biographical sketches and clippings about Grace Hechinger, correspondence, and speeches and writings, arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein chronologically
  - Biographical sketches and clippings., See also Biographical File, and Oversize File (Folder 72: 10)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Folder 72: 11)
    - 1963-1974 (Folder 72: 12)
  - Speeches and writings., See also Speeches and Writings and Oversize File for writings co-authored with Fred Hechinger
    - General (Folder 72: 13)
    - "Broadway's New Star," American Swedish Monthly, 1957 June. (Folder 72: 14)
    - "How to Be a Bride and Live Through It," Bride's World, 1958 April 27. (Folder 72: 15)
    - Review, "Good Schools Don't Just Happen," Parents' Magazine, 1961 February, NEA Magazine Report, 1961 April. (Folder 72: 16)
    - Participant, discussion, "Thunder of Tiny Feet: The Child in Our Society," Open Mind, WNBC Television, 1964 March 8. (Folder 72: 17)
      Typescript transcript and announcement in New York Times
    - Interview, WNBC Television and NBC Television Network, 1971 December 15. (Folder 72: 18)
      Typescript transcript
    - Review of Fredelle Maynard, Guiding Your Child to a More Creative Life; Lise Liepmann, Your Child's Sensory World; and Ruth Langdon Inglis, A Time to Learn: a Guide for Parents to the New Theories in Early Childhood Education, Learning, 1974 February. (Folder 72: 19)
    - "Sesame," Annual Education Review?, 1975 January. (Folder 72: 20)
- Subject File, 1971-1989. (Box 73)
  Brochures, correspondence, memoranda, pamphlets, printed matter, and reports, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - American Association for Higher Education (Folder 73: 1)
  - American Federation of Arts (Folder 73: 2)
  - Annie E. Casey Foundation (Folder 73: 3)
  - Children's Television Workshop (Folder 73: 4)
  - Choate Rosemary Hall (Folder 73: 5)
  - High/Scope Educational Research Foundation (Folder 73: 6)
  - Human ecology (Folder 73: 7)
  - Leadership (Folder 73: 8)
  - National Assembly on Foreign Language and International Studies (Folder 73: 9)
  - National Commission for Cooperative Education (Folder 73: 10)
  - National Commission on Testing and Public Policy (Folder 73: 11)
  - National Committee for Responsive Philanthropy (Folder 73: 12)
  - Nuclear nonproliferation (Folder 73: 13)
  - Policy Analysis for California Education (PACE) (Folder 73: 14)
  - Rockefeller Brothers Fund (Folder 73: 15)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (Folder 73: 16)
  - Scholastic, Inc. (Folder 73: 17)
  - Technology (Folder 73: 18)
  - Television (Folder 73: 19)
  - United World Colleges (Folder 73: 20)
  - William J. Donovan Memorial Foundation (Folder 73: 21)
  - WNYC (Folder 73: 22)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 73: 23-24)
    Includes brochures, clippings, memoranda from various organizations, and speeches and writings by others sent to Fred Hechinger
  - Miscellany. (Box-folder 74: 1)
- Photographs, 1933-1989.; See also Oversize File
  50 prints depicting Fred and Grace Hechinger and others, including Rex Cathcart, Robin Kidd, Walter Mondale, and Heitor Gurgulino de Souza.
  - One print depicting Fred Hechinger with Terry Connors, Undated (Folder 74: 2)
  - One print depicting Fred Hechinger printed in an announcement, Undated (Folder 74: 3)
  - Two prints depicting the Schloss Leopoldskron, home of the Salzburg Seminar, and fellows and faculty, including Rex Cathcart and Robbins Kidd, undated; one print depicting J. W. Peltason and James E. Olson, undated; one print depicting Robert L. Payton, undated; one print depicting William R. Sears (Folder 74: 4)
  - One print depicting a child's painting from Studio Elementary School Student Art Show, Undated (Folder 74: 5)
  - One unidentified print of a family?, Undated (Folder 74: 6)
  - One print depicting faculty of dismissed or furloughed German professors, New School for Social Research, New York Times, 1933 October 4 (Folder 74: 7)
  - Two prints depicting Fred and Grace Hechinger, 1963? (Folder 74: 8)
  - Two prints depicting Fred Hechinger and others, WCBS Television, 1963 August 25 (Folder 74: 9)
  - One print depicting Walter Mondale presenting a real apple in lieu of a crystal one to Beverly J. Bimes, St. Louis, Missouri, 1980 National Teacher of the Year award ceremony, White House, Washington, D.C., 1980 April 16; and five prints depicting unidentified individuals (Folder 74: 10)
  - One print depicting George Roberts, 1980 September 12 (Folder 74: 11)
  - One print depicting Beverly J. Bimes and three prints depicting her with students, 1981 February? (Folder 74: 12)
  - One print depicting Grolier's online encyclopedia, 1982 December? (Folder 74: 13)
  - Eight prints by Valerie J. Janesick depicting ceilings, walls, and windows of Rockefeller Institute? street corners in New York? music room, shadows on the corridor of a building, and statue of a lady in the park, 1983 (Folder 74: 14)
  - One print depicting Vincent Persichetti and Tamara Brooks, 1984 April? (Folder 74: 15)
  - One print depicting Sophia Tlali learning about television production, 1985 August? (Folder 74: 16)
  - One print depicting a group of school children holding a banner, "Heart Circus," as part of an art project highlighting big books, 1986 June? (Folder 74: 17)
  - Five prints depicting the proposed United Nations University, including one of Heitor Gurgulino de Souza, Rector, United Nations University, Tokyo, undated; one print depicting a model of the United Nations University building to be constructed in Japan, 1988; and three prints depicting the thirtieth session of the United Nations University Council at the UNU headquarters, Japan, 1987 December 11 (Folder 74: 18)
  - One print depicting Judith Kaplan with her students, 1988 February? (Folder 74: 19)
  - One print depicting a page from the 1989 March 15 issue of 7 Days magazine, which includes an ad from the company of Henry E. Nass (Folder 74: 20)
  - Three prints depicting students participating in the television contest Jeopardy along with their teachers and assistant principal, 1989 April? (Folder 74: 21)
- Computer Disk, 1985. (Folder 74: 22)
  "Orpheus A - B - C: The Poetry Processor," copyright Michael Newman, 1985. One 5.25-inch floppy disk
- Oversize File, 1950-1989.; See also Biographical File. (Box 75)
  Announcements of honorary degrees, posters, printed photograph, and speeches and writings by Fred Hechinger (and Grace Hechinger when so indicated), arranged alphabetically by physical form and therein by title for the speeches and writings.
  - Announcements
    - Address, National School Boards Association, Houston, Texas, 1977 March 26-29
    - Honorary degree from City College, New York, Times Talk, 1977 May-June
    - Honorary doctorate of Human Letters, Hood College (shared with Grace Hechinger), Maryland, Times Talk, 1989 October
  - Posters
    - Better Schools thanking Fred Hechinger, Undated
    - "Learning to Read Through the Arts Program," Conference Exhibition, Performing Arts and Film Festival, Board of Education, New York City, New York, 1986 May 28.
      Includes a letter from Jill Kauffmann, Business and Industry for the Arts in Education, Inc.
  - Printed photograph depicting meeting with news writing students, journalism laboratory, Long Island University, Brooklyn, New York, Times Talk, 1989 September
  - Speeches and writings
    - "America Is Her Promised Land," Sunday Herald, 1950 January 29.
    - "Germany: Flash Back to Disaster?" New York Herald Tribune, 1950 February 12.
    - "The Boydens of Deerfield," New York Herald Tribune, 1953 November 15.
    - "Tribute to Brandeis," acknowledgement of cooperation from various organizations, Sunday Herald, 1956 November 11.
    - "The Teen-Age Problem: A Prime Example" (with Grace Hechinger), New York Times Magazine, 1962 September 30.
    - "It's Teacher's Turn in the Corner," review of James B. Conant, The Education of American Teachers, New York Times Book Review, 1963 September 15.
    - "The City Schools: A Mixed Report Card," New York Times Magazine, 1964 June 14.
    - "The Flowering of a Campus Hybrid," New York Times Magazine, 1964 September 13.
    - "Homosexuality on Campus" (with Grace Hechinger), New York Times Magazine, 1978 March 12.
    - "A Servant of Church and Academe," Notre Dame Magazine, 1987 Spring.
    - Moderator, panel, "Keeping America Competitive: The Role of Education," New York Times Presidents Forum, New York, 1989 December 6.
      Printed announcement and report
- Scrapbooks, 1946-1963. (Box 76)
  Address; articles; clippings, correspondence, and reviews; and columns, by or relating to Fred Hechinger, arranged alphabetically and therein by titles of books, journals, or newspapers
  - Address, Educational Forum, 1954 May 11.
  - Articles from
    - Data Upsilon Quarterly, 1952
    - Harper's Magazine, 1948-1950
    - Military Government Journal, 1948-1954
    - News Bulletin, 1952-1953
    - The Park School Alumni Newsletter, 1953
    - The Reporter, 1949-1952
    - Saturday Review, 1948-1955
    - School Executive, 1954
    - This Week Magazine, 1946-1956.
      Includes interviews
    - Miscellany, 1948-1954
  - Clippings, correspondence, and reviews (Box 77)
    - An Adventure in Education: Connecticut Points the Way, 1956
    - The Big Red Schoolhouse, 1959 (Box 78)
  - Columns. (Box 79-81)
    Includes some articles and related materials
    - Amarillo Daily, Undated
    - Better Schools, 1956
    - Bridgeport Connecticut, 1947
    - Bridgeport Herald, 1947-1959
    - Case Alumnus, 1956
    - Fairfield News, Undated
    - Greenwich Time, 1956
    - Harper's Magazine, 1948
    - Herald Tribune Book Review, 1957
    - Kenyon Alumni Bulletin, 1956
    - NEA Journal, 1957
    - New York Herald Tribune, 1946-1963
    - New York Times, 1943-1947
    - Parents Magazine, 1956
    - Saturday Review, 1955-1956
    - Sunday Herald, 1946-1957
    - Washington Post, 1946-1949
    - This Week Magazine, 1946-1947
  - Miscellany. Announcements, articles, columns, and excerpts of speeches (Box 82)